Erwin Chargaff Papers 1929-1992 Mss.B.C37
American Philosophical Society
Erwin Chargaff Papers
1929-1992
Mss.B.C37
American Philosophical Society
56.0 Linear feet
A biochemist at Columbia University, Erwin Chargaff discovered the base-pairing regularities or "complementarity relationships" of nucleic acids that provided one of the key steps in developing a structural model for DNA. During his long career, Chargaff is credited with conclusively falsifying the tetranucleotide hypothesis; demonstrating the existence of a large number of DNA species; and creating the first descriptions of hypochromicity, hyperchromicity, and the denaturation of a DNA. In addition, Chargaff conducted important research on blood coagulation, lipids and lipoproteins, the metabolism of amino acids and inositol, and the biosynthesis of phosphotransferases. He retired to emeritus status in 1974 and remained active in research almost to the time of his death in June 2002. The Chargaff Papers are organized into ten series: I. Correspondence, 1931-1992; Ia. Correspondence, 1949-2002; IIa. Grants, 1930-1982; IIb. Subject Files, 1940-1984; IIc. Subject Files, 1946-2002; III. Works by Chargaff, 1929-1989; IIIa. Works by Chargaff, 1923-2002; IIIb. Reprints, 1977-1999; IV. Works by Others, 1936-1985; IVa. Works by Others, 1976-2002; V. Research Notes and Notebooks, 1929-1951; VI. Photographs, 1935-1977; VIa. Photographs, 1928-2002; VII. Audiovisual Materials; VIII. Awards and Certificates, 1958-2001; IX. Lecture Notes, 1942-1985; X. Personal Papers, [1880]-1985.
Chargaff, Erwin
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Erwin Chargaff was the first biochemist in America to develop a substantial research program centered around the genetic specificity of nucleic acids, research that formed a major chapter in the history of molecular biology. Having been one of a handful of life scientists in the mid-1940s to appreciate the significance of O. T. Avery's discovery that DNA was the transforming principle in pneumococci, Chargaff set out to probe the chemical properties of nucleic acids in relation to their biological specificity. By 1950 his finding that DNA could account for genetic specificity led to the demise of P. A. Levene's dominant tetranucleotide theory of DNA structure, which regarded DNA as ill-suited for carrying information. Chargaff's findings also eclipsed some of Max Bergmann's protein theories of biological specificity. Chargaff's work was a turning point in gene research from proteins to nucleic acids, and his laboratory at Columbia (in the biochemistry department headed by Hans Thacher Clarke) became a premier center for nucleic acids chemistry.
The Chargaff Papers document in detail the intellectual and social history of his research program. The collection contains records of Chargaff's investigations on rickettsia and typhus during the war years 1942-1945 as part of the OSRD projects, as well as material on his research on the chemistry of blood coagulants; these are important sources on the relation of the life sciences to the military. There is a great deal of material on the crucial years 1945-1950, during which time Chargaff reoriented his research program toward the chemistry of heredity, and records that include rejections of his research proposals by several foundations.
After 1950, with the increased interest in nucleic acids, Chargaff gained recognition and acquired his own research facilities at Columbia, the Laboratory of Cell Chemistry. Also included is material on nucleic acids research, the rise of molecular genetics, and Chargaff's role in these developments. Of interest are his exchanges with pharmaceutical houses (circa 1940s-1950s), including Hoffmann-La Roche, Bio-Vin, Upjohn, Eli Lilly, Rohm and Haas, and Parke-Davis, communications highlighting the links between academic and industrial biochemistry. The remainder of the correspondence (1960s) reflects the expansion of Chargaff's administrative activities and his increased influence within the life sciences.
Unfortunately there is little material on Chargaff's years in Germany or the period 1934-1941, when he first established his research program at Columbia. But being a prolific writer and a vociferous critic of American culture, Chargaff frequently compared his European and American experiences. His correspondence with many European colleagues throughout the 1940s and 1950s deals with issues surrounding the intellectual migration and reflects this cross-cultural perspective.
Series I. Correspondence:
Anderson, Rudolph John, 1879-1961 Correspondence (17 items) 1943-1961 English
Astbury, William Thomas, 1898-1961 Correspondence (14 items) 1951-1961 English
Barzun, Jacques, b. 1907 Correspondence (31 items) 1958-1978 English
Bergmann, Ernst David, 1903-1975 Correspondence (10 items) 1947-1952 English
Bernhard, Karl Correspondence (20 items) 1945-1949, 1964 German
Bondi, Alfred Correspondence (26 items) 1949-1966 German
Brachet, J. (Jean), 1909-1998 Correspondence (24 items) 1949-1974 French
Brawerman, George Correspondence (191 items) 1951-1976 English
Cohen, Seymour S. (Seymour Stanley), 1917- Correspondence (96 items) 1942-1982 French
Cohn, Waldo E. Correspondence (3 folders) 1950-1980 English
Columbia University Correspondence (10 folders) 1941-1989 English
Crick, Francis, 1916-2004 Correspondence (6 items) 1954, 1974 English
Davidson, John Norman Correspondence (4 folders) 1947-1972 English
Doty, Paul Correspondence (21 items) 1952-1953, 1966 English
Ehrensvard, Gosta Carl Henrik, Greve, 1910-1980 Correspondence (64 items) 1949-1959 English
Elson, David Correspondence (128 items) 1949-1974 English
Frazer, Alastair Campbell, 1909-1969 Correspondence (37 items) 1946-1964 English
Gamow, George, 1904-1968 ( Correspondence regarding biochemistry and organic chemistry, human genetics, molecular genetics, and the RNA Tie Club.) Correspondence (21 items) 1954-1955 English
Gustafson, Tryggve Correspondence (24 items) 1949-1954 English
Haurowitz, Felix, 1896-1987 Correspondence (17 items) 1950-1960 German
Hawthorne, J. N. (John Nigel) Correspondence (2 folders) 1951-1984 English
Hoffmann-LaRoche, Inc. Correspondence (81 items) 1942-1971 German
Horstadius, Sven, 1898-1996 Correspondence (41 items) 1949-1954 English
Hotchkiss, Rollin Douglas, 1911-2004 Correspondence (18 items) 1949-1979 English
Kendrew, John C. (John Cowdery), 1917-1997 Correspondence (43 items) 1951-1974 English
Lederberg, Joshua Correspondence (8 items) 1950-1958 English
Linderstrom-Lang, Kaj Ulrik, 1896-1959 Correspondence (17 items) 1951-1959 English
Monroy, Alberto Correspondence (53 items) 1950-1985 English
Parke, Davis and Company Correspondence (30 items) 1935-1961 English
Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994 ( Correspondence regarding Columbia University, requests for aid in finding positions, biochemistry and organic chemistry, editorial matters, professional associations, and the Nobel Prize.) Correspondence (10 items) 1945-1972 English
Pirie, N. W. (Norman Wingate), 1907-1997 Correspondence (50 items) 1945-1983 English
Pollock, Martin Rivers, 1914-1999 Correspondence (13 items) 1962-1971 English
Reichstein, Tadeusz, 1897-1996 Correspondence (50 items) 1947-1954, 1964 German
Rittenberg, David, 1906-1970 Correspondence (21 items) 1954-1966 English
Rohm and Haas Company Correspondence (11 items) 1945-1953 English
Runnstrom, John Axel Mauritz, 1888-1971 Correspondence (102 items) 1947-1971 English
Saukkonen, Jussi J. Correspondence (64 items) 1956-1968 English
Schmidt, Gerhard Correspondence (81 items) 1944-1976 English
Slater, Donald W. Correspondence (4 items) 1959, 1971 English
Tamm, Christoph, 1923- Correspondence (1 folder) 1950-1975 German
Todd, Alexander R. (Alexander Robertus), 1907-1997 Correspondence (26 items) 1945-1957 English
Upjohn Company Correspondence (8 items) 1947-1948 English
Vendrely, Roger Correspondence (11 items) 1951-1971 French
Viobin Corporation Correspondence (15 items) 1948, 1950 English
Vischer, Ernst Benedikt Correspondence (100 items) 1947-1971 German
Wilkins, Maurice, 1916-2004 Correspondence (18 items) 1951-1954 English
Series IIa. Grants:
Lilly Research Laboratories Correspondence (19 items) 1952-1955 English
Office of Scientific Research and Development ( Investigations on rickettsia and typhus during the war years, 1942-1945.) Correspondence (12 folders) 1942-1947 English
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Chargaff Papers were donated to the APS by Erwin Chargaff in 1975. An extensive description of the original order of the collection was written in 1977 by Pnina Abir-Am for Survey of Sources for the History of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology. To see this original description, consult the manuscripts librarian. In 1987 the papers were donated by Chargaff. In 1987 additional papers were deposited by Chargaff. These papers were interfiled in the collection and the finding aid updated by Miriam B. Spectre. In 2002, a final deposit was made upon Chargaff's death, and the finding aid revised to reflect this deposit.
Scope and Contents note
The Erwin Chargaff Papers (1929-1992) contain correspondence; grant material; subject files; manuscripts of published and unpublished works by Chargaff; papers by colleagues, correspondents and students; research notes by Chargaff and students; photographs and negatives; audiovisual materials; lecture notes; awards and certificates; and personal documents. The majority of the collection prior to 1990 is in English, but there is a significant amount of material in German. After 1990, the bulk of the collection is in German. These folders are marked "In German" or "Some in German" as appropriate. While the collection spans the years 1929 to 1992, the bulk of the collection dates from the 1940s to the 1970s, although there are a significant number of papers from 1990-2002. Papers that were accessioned in the 2002 deposit have been kept separate in their own subseries except for correspondence with correspondents for whom a file already existed in the original Series I. Correspondence with these correspondents were interfiled with the original correspondence. Some of the papers in the 2002 accession include early documents, letters, date books and other works by Chargaff.
The papers (113 boxes; 56 linear feet) are divided into ten series:
Series I Correspondence, 1931-1992 30 linear feet
Series Ia Correspondence, 1949-2002 5 boxes; 2.5 linear feet
Series IIa Grants, 1930-1982 3.5 linear feet
Series IIb Subject files, 1940-1984 1.5 linear feet
Series IIc Subject Files, 1946-2002 1 box; .25 linear feet
Series III Works by Chargaff, 1929-1989 15.5 linear feet
Series IIIa Works by Chargaff, 1923-2002 5 boxes; 2 linear feet
Series IIIb Works by Chargaff: Reprints, 1977-1999 3 boxes; 1 linear feet
Series IV Works by others, 1936-1985 1.25 linear feet
Series IVa Works by Others, 1976-2002 1 box; .5 linear feet
Series V Research notes, 1929-1951 2.25 linear feet
Series VI Photographs, 1935-1977 1.75 linear feet
Series VIa Photographs and Negatives, 1928-2002 11 boxes; 2 linear feet
Series VII Audiovisual materials 2 boxes; .5 linear feet
Series VIII Awards and Certificates, 1958-2001 7 boxes; 4 linear feet
Series IX Lecture Notes, 1942-1985 3 boxes; 1.25 linear feet
Series X Personal Papers, [1880]-1985 1 box; .5 linear feet
Series I-X Oversized materials 2 boxes; 1 linear feet
Biographical/Historical note
One of the foremost contributors to a modern understanding of the nucleic acids, Erwin Chargaff was born in Czernowitz, Austria on August 11, 1905. After receiving a doctorate from the University of Vienna in 1928, he accepted a position at Yale University, where he became the Milton Campbell Research Fellow in Organic Chemistry from 1928 to 1930. From Yale, Chargaff returned to Europe for four years, spending 1930-1933 as Assistant in Charge of Chemistry for the Department of Bacteriology and Public Health at the University of Berlin and 1933-1934 as Research Associate at the Institut Pasteur in Paris.
After his early wanderings, Chargaff settled down to spend his most productive and creative years in association with Columbia University. Starting as a Research Associate in the Department of Biochemistry in 1935, he climbed the academic ladder to Assistant Professor in 1938 and Professor in 1952, eventually becoming departmental chair (1970-1974), and receiving Professor Emeritus (1974).
After reading Oswald Avery's seminal 1944 paper identifying DNA as the hereditary material, Chargaff reoriented his laboratory to the study of the structure and function of nucleic acids and their components using the new chromatographic techniques developed by John Martin and Richard Synge. By 1950, in research funded in part by the Office of Scientific Research and Development, the United States Public Health Service, and the American Cancer Society, Chargaff made a discovery of critical importance, regardless of the source, the amounts of adenine and thymine were equal, as were the amounts of cytosine and guanine. The discovery of this distinctive pattern of base-pairing regularities in DNA (Chargaff's "complementarity relationships") provided a compelling rejection of the tetranucleotide hypothesis and demonstrated the potential for the existence of a large number of species of DNA, however Chargaff made little headway in unraveling the causes of base regularities. In later years, he argued that he had planted the seeds for the double helix in the minds of Watson and Crick during a luncheon meeting in May 1952 to discuss his results, however Chargaff himself failed to make the connections between these regularities and base pairing. In later work, however, he was credited with providing the first demonstrations of hypochromicity, hyperchromicity, and the denaturation of a DNA, and his lab also conducted important research on blood coagulation, lipids and lipoproteins, the metabolism of amino acids and inositol, and the biosynthesis of phosphotransferases.
From the late 1950s, Chargaff grew increasingly disillusioned with molecular biology, the field that he had helped found, lamenting what he perceived as the subordination of biochemistry to molecular pursuits, famously accusing molecular biologists of practicing biochemistry without a license. In later life, he became an outspoken critic of the newer biotechnologies involving cloning, genetic manipulation, and gene transfer, decrying the poverty of bioethical standards in the field and claiming that molecular biology was "running riot and doing things that can never be justified." He spoke and wrote extensively against the use of microbiology in genetic engineering, primarily for a European market, describing himself as "the unwilling cofounder of a science that [he] abhorred." During these years, Chargaff also returned to his youthful interest in language and satire, in particular the works of Karl Kraus, the Viennese satirist.
Throughout his career, Chargaff regularly served as visiting lecturer and professor at other institutions, including the Wenner Gren Center at the University of Stockholm (1949); several universities in Japan (1958); the Universities of Rio de Janeiro, Sao Paulo, and Recife in Brazil (1959); and the Collège de France, where he held the Albert Einstein Chair (1965). He gave the Plenary Congress Lecture at the International Biochemistry Congress in Vienna (1958); the Harvey Society Lecture (1956); the Jesup Lectures at Columbia University (1959); and the Miescher Memorial Lecture in Basel (1969). He was on the Committee on Growth of the National Research Council (1952-1954), and he was also on the Advisory Council on Biology at Oak Ridge National Laboratory (1958-1967). His numerous awards and honors include the Pasteur Medal (1949), the Carl Neuberg Medal (1958), the Société de Chimie Biologique Medal (1961), the Charles Leopold Mayer Prize (1963), the H.P. Heineken Prize (1964), the Bertner Foundation Award (1965), the Gregor Mendel Medal (1973), the National Medal of Science (1974), the New York Academy of Medicine Medal (1980), and Columbia University's Distinguished Service Award (1982). He was also awarded an honorary ScD from Columbia University (1976) and an honorary doctorate from the University of Basel (1976).
Chargaff also was awarded numerous awards and honors for his work as an essayist and ethicist during his later years, including the Grosse Goldene Ehrenzeichen für Verdienste um die Republik Osterreich (1990), Osterreichische Ehrenzeichen für Wissenschaft und Kunst (1994), Preis der Stadt Wien für Publizistik (1994), Friedrick Märker-Preis für Essayisten (2000) and the Ehrenmedaille der Bundeshauptstadt Wien in Gold (2001).
Chargaff has been a member of the editorial boards for Biochimica et Biophysica Acta, Columbia University's Forum, and American Chemical Society Monographs, as well as a member of the advisory board for Experimental Cell Research. He was a member of the Royal Swedish Physiographic Society (1959), the American Academy of Arts and Sciences (1961), the National Academy of Sciences (1965), the American Philosophical Society (1979), and many other professional organizations.
Chargaff published almost 500 articles in English, German, French and Italian. Most were published during his years at Columbia, some as collaborations with his students and colleagues. He also published several books during this time, including three volumes called the Nucleic Acids in 1955 and 1960 with J. N. Davidson; Essays on Nucleic Acids in 1963; and Voices in the Labyrinth: Dialogues Around the Study of Nature in 1977. His autobiographical Heraclitean Fire was published in 1978. In his later years, he published numerous essays, primarily written in German, and frequently made television and radio appearances in Europe, arguing against the use of molecular biology in genetic engineering.
Chargaff married Vera Broido in 1928, with whom he had one child, Thomas, and became an American citizen in 1940. After a falling out with the department at Columbia following his retirement to emeritus status in 1974, Chargaff moved his laboratory to Columbia's affiliate, Roosevelt Hospital, where he continued to work until 1992. He died on June 20, 2002 at the age of 96.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
American Association for the Advancement of Science Correspondence (58 items) 1949-1981
American Institute of Biological Sciences Correspondence (23 items) 1949-1958
Beadle, George Wells Correspondence (4 items) 1961, 1966
Biochimica et Biophysica Acta Records (39 folders) 1951-1972, 1981
Britain. Parliament Subcommittee on Genetic Engineering Correspondence (3 items) 1979
Chargaff, Erwin -- Bibliographies Manuscripts (2 folders) Circa 1930s - Circa 1970s
Chargaff, Erwin -- Research notes Manuscripts (2.25 linear feet) 1929-1951
Columbia University Records (14 folders) 1941-1989
Ephrussi, Boris Correspondence (10 items) 1957-1965
Gamow, George Correspondence (21 items) 1954-1955
Judson, Horace Freeland Correspondence (10 items) 1976-1981
McClintock, Barbara Correspondence (2 items) 1952
Medawar, Peter Brian Correspondence (7 items) 1978-1984
Medvedev, Zhores A. Correspondence (6 items) 1964
National Academy of Sciences Records (10 folders) 1950, 1959-1985
National Academy of Sciences Records (6 folders) 1963-1976
Olby, Robert Cecil Correspondence (10 items) 1967-1973
Pauling, Linus Correspondence (10 items) 1945-1972
Sonneborn, Tracy M. Correspondence (8 items) 1959-1963
Union Carbide Corporation Correspondence (4 folders) 1945-1976
American Cancer Society.; American Chemical Society.; Anderson, Rudolph J.; Barzun, Jacques, 1907-2012; Burris, Robert H. (Robert Harza), 1914-; Carter, Herbert E.; Cohn, Waldo E.; Columbia University.; Crick, Francis, 1916-2004; Davidson, J. N. (James Norman); Doty, Paul; Edsall, John T., (John Tileston), 1902-2002; Gamow, George, 1904-1968; Hardin, Garrett James, 1915-2003; Kusch, Polykarp, 1911-1993; Lederberg, Joshua; Lederer, Edgar.; McClintock, Barbara, 1902-1992; National Academy of Sciences. (U.S.); Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994; Perutz, Max F.; Runnstrom, John.; Schmidt, Gerhard; Schmitt, Francis Ottom, 1903-; Stanacev, Nikola Z.; Straus, Werner; United States. Office of Scientific Research and Development; United States. Public Health Service.; Waelsch, Heinrich B.; Wald, George; Watson, James D., 1928-; Biochemistry.; Biochimica et Biophysica Acta; DNA; Inositol; Laboratory notebooks; Lipoproteins; Nucleic acids; Nucleic acids--Structure; Phosphotransferases; Photoprints; Recombinant DNA
- Series I. Correspondence, 1931-1992; 30 linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming and outgoing manuscript and typescript letters, carbons, telegrams, and postcards generated during Chargaff's career. The largest series in the collection, Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name and then chronologically within each folder. When a correspondence file includes letters to a third party (i.e., not Chargaff), the name is indicated on the container list by using an indent under the folder title.
  Unidentified correspondence has been filed as "Unidentified" and is arranged chronologically.
  Enclosed manuscripts have been removed from this series and placed in Series III or IV as appropriate. As with the reprints, a photocopy of the title page was filed with the original letter. Cross-references are also given for enclosed photographs, which have been removed to Series VI. The bulk of this series covers the 1940s to the 1970s. Correspondence regarding grants has been filed in Series IIa under the name of the granting agency.
  Correspondents include biochemists, chemists, molecular biologists, students, publishers, and European colleagues. Among the topics covered in this series are: nucleic acids, recombinant DNA, denaturation of DNA, and blood clotting. There is a substantial amount of correspondence regarding the administration of Chargaff's research laboratories at Columbia University and at Roosevelt Hospital, his work as editor for the journal, Biochimica et Biophysica Acta, and his affiliations with many scientific organizations, such as the National Academy of Sciences and the American Chemical Society. Also included is correspondence with various pharmaceutical companies, such as Hoffmann-LaRoche, Parke-Davis, Rohm and Haas, Upjohn, and Viobin, regarding research material. Because of Chargaff's frequent trips to Europe, there is a substantial amount of correspondence with his students about laboratory research taking place in his absence. For lists of these correspondents, see the cross-references on the folders of Emmy Bloch, Charlotte Green, and Elisabeth Van Vendeloo. For lists of correspondence related to recombinant DNA, see the cross-references on the folder labeled "Recombinant DNA" in Series IIb. Correspondence regarding Chargaff's work on the Advisory Council on Biology at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory is filed under "Union Carbide Corporation." Letters of reference are filed under the name of the person who is the subject of the letter.
  Anderson, Rudolph J.
  Anshen, Ruth Nanda
  Barzun, Jacques
  Bearn, Alexander G.
  Berg, Paul
  Bloch, Konrad
  Burris, Robert H.
  Calvin, Melvin
  Carter, Herbert E.
  Chagas, Carlos
  Cohn, Waldo E.
  Crick, Francis H.C.
  Davidson, J. Norman
  Doty, Paul
  Du Vignead, Vincent
  Edsall, John T.
  Fuller, Buckminster
  Gamow, George
  Hardin, Garrett
  Humphrey, Hubert H.
  Kennedy, Robert F.
  Khorana, Har Gobind
  Kirk, Grayson
  Kornberg, Arthur
  Kusch, Polykarp
  Lederberg, Joshua
  Lederer, Edgar
  Luck, J. Murray
  McCarty, Maclyn
  McClintock, Barbara
  Merton, Robert K.
  Ochoa, Severo
  Pauling, Linus
  Perutz, Max F.
  Prelog, Vladimir
  Runnström, John
  Schmidt, Gerhard
  Schmitt, Francis O.
  Smith, Emil L.
  Stanacev, Nikola Z.
  Straus, Werner
  Waelsch, Heinrich B.
  Wald, George
  Watson, James D.
  Weinberg, Alvin M.